Benjamin E. Neal Papers
Benjamin E. Neal Papers
1901-1999
1901-1904
Neal, Benjamin E.
5 linear ft.
Papers of the American who taught English in the Philippines from 1901-1904. Correspondence, diaries, account books, photographs, postcards, and memorabilia related to Neal's work in the Philippines.
149355
Biographical History
Benjamin E. Neal (1879-1966) was a native of Buffalo, New York. He graduated from Syracuse University in 1901 and joined the Thomasites, a group of five hundred American teachers sent to the Philippines by the U.S. government in August 1901 to establish a new public school system there. The group was known as "Thomasites" after the ship that brought them to Manila, the USS Thomas. Neal taught English in the Philippines from 1901-1904. He was a Syracuse University alumni trustee from 1923 to 1934.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Benjamin E. Neal Papers consists of correspondence, diaries, memorabilia, photographs, printed material, and writings, most of which pertain to Neal's work with the so-called Thomasites, teaching English in the Philippines.
Correspondence is both personal and professional, including letters and postcards to friends and family, official documents relating to Neal's teaching work, and so on. Numerous letters of recommendation testify to Neal's scholarship, integrity, and abilities.
Diaries cover the entirety of Neal's time in the Philippines, and include observations on his students and colleagues as well as on Filipino culture and community.
Memorabilia contains items relating to Neal's travels to and from the Philippines, including scrapbooks, posters, and souvenir booklets, as well as one item relating to Syracuse University, Neal's alma mater.
A large number of Photographs, including many hand-tinted albumen prints, document Neal's interest in the people he met and the places where he taught and visited. These include China, Japan, the Philippines, and major cities of Europe (London, Rome, Paris, etc.). There are also a few family photos, including Neal's grandparents, two men in front of a shopfront "Neal, Clarke & Neal," and one identified on the back as "The Neal Homestead built in 1850."
Printed material contains books and clippings. Three of the books are directly related to the so-called Thomasites (among these are a souvenir booklet, "The Log of the Thomas", with text and photos of the voyage). The fourth concerns American efforts in the Philippines and mentions Neal.
Writings contains a single document, an essay on "Memory" written by Neal for a college course.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, the remainder of the material alphabetically by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Neal, Benjamin E.; English language -- Study and teaching -- Philippines.; Philippines -- Civilization -- American influences.; Philippines -- Description and travel.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Essays.; Photographs.; Postcards.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jean Burmaster Palmer, Elton and Mary Elizabeth (Neal) Burmaster, and Mrs. Benjamin Neal, 1967, 1969, 2016.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - General, 1901-1904 (Box 1)
  - Postcards, Apr 1904 - Jul 1905; first folder includes an itemized list, provided by donor; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Recommendations, 1901-1904; letters of recommendation for Neal from a variety of people, including former teachers and colleagues (Box 1)
- Diaries
  - Diaries, 1901-1904; some include laid-in correspondence, notes, other papers; 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - Diaries, transcribed, 1901-1904; photocopy of typed transcript of diaries, appears to be complete (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Bamboo tubes, 2 items (Oversize 1)
  - Calendar
  - Military posters
  - Scrapbook of picture postcards (Oversize 2)
  - Syracuse University, 1901 (Box 2)
  - Travels, 1901-1904; Philippines, Japan, Germany; includes an issue of "The Briny Budget," a newsletter published on board the Thomas (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - China (Box 2)
  - Family (Box 2)
  - Hawaii (Box 2)
  - Japan, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Philippines (I) (Box 2)
  - Philippines (II, III, and IV) (Box 3)
  - Philippines (V) (Oversize 1)
  - Return trip from Philippines, 1904; London, Paris, Rome, etc. (Box 4)
  - Syracuse University (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, 1904-1905 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 4)
- Printed material
  - Books
    - Compulsory education in the Philippines / Antonio Isidro, Juan Canave, Priscila Manalang, Matilde Valdes, 1953; signed and inscribed by Valdes to Neal (Box 4)
    - The log of the Thomas, 1901; souvenir booklet, including text, photographs, and lists of passengers and crew; 2 copies (Box 4)
    - In our image: America's empire in the Philippines / Stanley Karnow, 1999; Neal is mentioned on page 204 (Box 4)
    - Tales of the American teachers in the Philippines / Geronima Pecson, Maria Racelis (ed.s), includes essay by Frank Laubach (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1951; front page of Manila newspaper with letter from one of the American teachers; newspaper photograph of Neal at his 50th college reunion (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Essay on memory, handwritten, apparently for a college course on pedagogy (Box 4)